Preliminary Guide to the Joshua Heller prospectuses and ephemera collection, 1911-2015 MS2337
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Joshua Heller prospectuses and ephemera collection
1911-2015
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Heller, Joshua
MS2337
5.5 Linear Feet
Collection consists of prospectuses and multiple forms of ephemera, including postcards, posters, flyers, and programs related to various book presses and bookbinders, as well as rare book and press event materials. It also contains correspondence to and from Joshua Heller. Thre is a series of correspondence sent to Joshua and Phyllis Heller from artist Susan Allix. The collection dates from 1911-2015. These prospectuses and ephemera are associated mainly with fine (also known as small and/or private) presses, although academic and commercial presses are represented. The presses in this collection are located mainly in the United States and United Kingdom, along with other nations such as Australia. Fine, small, or private presses are generally owned by an individual or small group and tend to publish items of distinctive content or form. These presses may focus on publishing unconventional writings, artists' books, illustrated literary texts, little magazines, and other unique items. Fine presses often generate limited runs of works that appeal to the tastes of the printer and a select audience, rather than producing items of broad commercial interest. Also characteristic of fine presses is meticulous attention to craftsmanship with regard to materials and process. Exceptional design as well as the use of premium or handmade paper, high quality inks, and traditional printing methods (such as letterpress) is often emphasized. These presses may also employ modern printing techniques (such as laser printing), while maintaining an eye for excellent design and inventive form and content. In addition to their practical purposes, many prospectuses and other items in this collection are themselves works of fine printing and design. These objects may utilize traditional printing methods, as well as high quality paper, ink, typography, and illustration.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joshua Heller, 25 March 2015 (2015.020)
Collection Organization
Organized into 4 series: Prospectuses, Material related to presses and bookbinders, Event material, and Correspondence from Susan Allix
Biographical / Historical
Joshua and Phyllis Heller operated Joshua Heller Rare Books out of their home in Washington DC. The business closed from 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of prospectuses (a printed document that advertises or describes bookselling endeavors) and various forms of ephemera, including postcards, posters, flyers, and programs related to various presses and bookbinders, as well as rare book and press event materials. It also contains correspondence to and from Joshua Heller. There is a series related to correspondence sent to Joshua and Phyllis Heller from artist Susan Allix. The collection dates from 1911-2015.
Antiquarian booksellers; Books; Booksellers and bookselling; Postcards; Prospectuses -- Washington (D.C.).; Heller, Joshua
- Prospectuses, 1970-2015; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains prospectuses for various book presses and book binders. The series dates from 1970-2015.
  - The Alembric Press, 1986; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anachronic Edition, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Antiquariaat Frits Knuf, 1985; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arif Press, 1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arion Press, 1987-1988; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Basilisk Press Ltd., 1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Bieler Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bird and Bull Press, 1987-2001; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Black Stone Press, 2015; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Black Pennell Press, 1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bombshelter Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Book Club of California, 1986-2005; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brindabella, 1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Callaway Editions, 1981; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Canberra Brindabella Press, 1992-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Camberwell Press, 1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chama Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Chamberwell Press, 1986; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Circle Press, 1986; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The Catawba Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Center for Education, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chilmark Press, 1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Chimaera Press, 1986; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Chiswick Book Shop Inc., n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Consolidated/Drake Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Coyote Love Press, 1990; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Curwen Press, 1981, 1988; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dieu Donne Press, 1993-2012; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Dodman Press, 1983; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Doppler Press, 1980; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Dou Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Elaine Kowalsky, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Elmete Press, 1978; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Elston Press, 1997; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Emanon Press, 2011; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Erespin Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Eureka Books, 1987; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ex Ophida, 1986; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fleece Press, 1986; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Florin Press, 1988; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Flying Fish Press, 1992; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Flying Pyramid Press, 2015; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Flying Sugar Press, 1994-1995; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The Geary Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - The Gehenna Press, 1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Gillian Jason Gallery, 1992; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Gregynog Press, 1989-2006; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The Grenfell Press, 1986; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Grolier Club, 2002; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Holloway Press, 1997; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hanborough Parrot Press, 1990-1991; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, 1986; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Hayloft Press, 1983; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Heavenly Monkey, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Hermann, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Hermit Press, 1987-1988; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Inanna Press (1/2), 1992-1999; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Inanna Press (2/2), 1992-1999; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Inky Parrot Press, 1984-1986; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - James Linden Editions (1/2), 1992; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - James Linden Editions (2/2), 1992; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Jason and Rhodes, 1995; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Jihae Kwon, 2014; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Kaldeway Press, 1988, 1991; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Ives Street Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Kat Ran Press, 1997, 2002; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Ken Campbell, 1978-1990; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Libanus Press, 1986-1990; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Lone Oak Press, 2005; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Lutyens Trust, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Macmillan Publishers Limited, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Meadow Press, 1986; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The Merrion Press, 1978; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Michael Mundy, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Midnight Paper Sales, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - New Pyramid Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Ninja Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Occassional Works, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - The Old School Press, 1994-1995; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - The Old Stile Press, 1986-1987; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Osband Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Paradise Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Partick Press, 1987; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Pendomer Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Pennyroyal Press, 1985-1986; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Pennyroyal Caxton Press, 1999; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Perpetua Press, 1987; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Perdix Press, 1985; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Peter and the Wolf Editions, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Petrarch Press (1/2), 1987-1993; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Petrarch Press (2/2), 1987-1993; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Pie Tree Press, 1998; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The Plough Press, 1986-1987; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - The Press at Colorado College, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - The Press at the Humanities Research Center, 1987; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - The Press of Appletree Alley, 1987; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - The Press of the Nightowl, 1990; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Press on Scroll Road, 2002; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Prospectus without a press mentioned, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Quercus Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Rampant Lions Press, 1985; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Raphael Fodde Editions, 2000; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Red Angel Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Richard Bigus-Labyrinth Editions, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Robin Price, 1990-1994; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Rocket Press, 1983-1988; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Rulon-Miller Books, Inc., 1988; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Russell Maret, 2001; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Sacramento Book Collectors Club, 1986; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Scarab Press, 1980; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Scolar Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Sea Pen Press and Paper Mill, 1987; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - The September Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Sherwin Beach Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Skelton's Press Limited, 1983; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Simon J.F. King, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Simplemente Maria Press, 2000; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Sixth Chamber Press, 1986; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Solo Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - The Southern Typothetae, 1986; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - The Starwheel Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Stone and Lorson, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Stone House Press, 1985; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - The Tabard Private Press, 1986; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - The Tern Press (1/2), 1985-1991; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - The Tern Press (2/2), 1985-1991; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Three Ravens Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - The Typophiles, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Valerie Parry, 1985; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - W. Thomas Taylor, 1983-1987; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Warwick Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - The Whittington Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Wild Carrot Letterpress, 1993; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - The Yellow Barn Press, 1993; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - The Yolla Bolly Press, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Zeitlin and Ver Brugge, 1981; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Material related to presses and bookbinders, 1911-2010; 1959-1990; Series 2
  This series contains various forms of ephemera, including postcards, posters, flyers, and programs related to book presses and bookbinders. It also includes correspondence to and from Joshua Heller. The series dates from 1911-2010.
  - Articles and Booklets featuring Multiple Presses, 1985-1986; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Book as Art" Exhibition Programs, 1994-2000; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Brighton Press, 1994; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Bruce Rogers, 1959; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Catalogues and Published Writings about Artists' and Rare Books (1/2), 1961-1983; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Catalogues and Published Writings about Artists' and Rare Books (2/2), 1961-1983; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Charles Ricketts, n.d., undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Cheshire House, Inc., 1990; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Chiswick Press, 1911; Seires 2 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Curwen Press, n.d., undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - David Jones, 1959-1980; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - E. McKnight Kauffer, n.d., undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Edward Bawden, 1979-1989; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Eric Gill, 1963-1992; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Ernest Gimson, n.d., undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Fritz Eichenberg, 1990; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - "Guild of Book Workers Journal", 1999; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Hague and Gill Limited, 1938; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Henry Noel Humphreys, n.d., undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Hermann Zapf, n.d., undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Hilary Pepler and The Saint Dominic's Press, 1965; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Joseph Cundall, n.d., undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Material Related to Various Bookbinders, 1961-1993; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Merivale Editions, n.d., undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of British Printers, c. 1985; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Posters, 1982-2010; Series 2 (Flat box 1)
  - The Press of Appletree Alley, n.d., undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - The Private Press, 1938-1985; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - The Rampan Lions Press, n.d., undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Reverend Edward M. Catich, 1969-1976; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Rocket Press, 1985; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Rocky Stinehour, 1988; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Rowland Emett, 1990; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - The Shakespeare Head Press, 1916-1924; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Saint Albert's Press, n.d., undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - St. Dominic's Press, 1979; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Sydney M. Cockerell, 1987; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Tern Press, 1978; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - The Tidal Press, 1986; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Three Private Presses, 1979; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Vincent Fitz Gerald and Company, 1982-1985; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Ward Ritchie, 1987; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Westerham Press, 1974; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Event material, 1986-2005; Series 3
  This series includes postcards, posters, flyers, and programs related to rare book and press event materials. The series dates from 1986-2005.
  - Artist and Exhibition Booklets, 1990-2005; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Gallery Exhibition's Publicity, 1986-1993; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Posters, 1992-2000; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Folder data_value_missing_7f7445efad77e1123e62f93fe77630c1)
- Correspondence from Susan Allix, 1988-2014; Series 4
  Arranged in original order. Most folders are in a loose chronological order and sometimes in a loose reverse chronological order.
  This series contains letters, postcards, and some printed mateirals sent to Joshua and Phyllis Heller from artist Susan Allix. The materials date from 1988-2014.
  - [Correspondence from Susan Allix] [1/2], 1988-2000; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - [Correspondence from Susan Allix] [2/2], 1994-2013; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - [Correspondence from Susan Allix] [1/3], 2007-2014; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - [Correspondence from Susan Allix] [2/3], 2001-2005; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - [Correspondence from Susan Allix] [3/3], 1998-2001; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 5)